<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"
[
<!ENTITY RFC0826 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0826.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2385 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2385.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3352 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3352.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4272 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4272.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4301 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4301.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4861 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4861.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5082 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5082.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5925 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5925.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6830 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6830.xml">
<!ENTITY LLDP SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.acee-idr-lldp-peer-discovery.xml">
<!ENTITY BGP-OSPF SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.acee-ospf-bgp-rr.xml">
<!ENTITY L3DL SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl.xml">
<!ENTITY L3DL-ULPC SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl-ulpc.xml">
<!ENTITY AUTO-SESSION SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.raszuk-idr-bgp-auto-session-setup.xml">
<!ENTITY RASZUK-AUTODISCOVERY SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.raszuk-idr-bgp-auto-discovery.xml">
<!ENTITY XU-AUTODISCOVERY SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.xu-idr-neighbor-autodiscovery.xml">
<!ENTITY LSOE SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lsvr-lsoe.xml">
<!ENTITY L3DL-SIGNING SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl-signing.xml">
]>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-dt-idr-bgp-autoconf-considerations-00" ipr="trust200902">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="BGP Peer Auto-Config Reqs">Requirements and Considerations in BGP Peer Auto-Configuration</title>
        <author fullname="Randy Bush" initials="R." surname="Bush">
            <organization>Arrcus, Inc. &amp; Internet Initiative Japan</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>5147 Crystal Springs</street>
                    <city>Bainbridge Island</city>
                    <region>WA</region>
                    <code>98110</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>randy@psg.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Jie Dong" initials="J." surname="Dong">
            <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Huawei Campus, No. 156 Beiqing Road</street>
                    <city>Beijing</city>
                    <code>100095</code>
                    <country>China</country>
                </postal>
                <email>jie.dong@huawei.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author role="editor" fullname="Jeffrey Haas" initials="J." surname="Haas">
            <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1133 Innovation Way</street>
                    <city>Sunnyvale</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>94089</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>jhaas@juniper.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author role="editor" fullname="Warren Kumari" initials="W." surname="Kumari">
            <organization>Google</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1600 Amphitheatre Parkway</street>
                    <city>Mountain View</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>94043</code>
                    <country>US</country>
                </postal>
                <email>warren@kumari.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date day="9" month="February" year="2021" />
        <abstract>
            <t>This draft is an exploration of the requirements, the
            alternatives, and trade-offs in BGP peer auto-discovery at various
            layers in the stack. It is based on discussions in the IDR WG BGP
            Autoconf Design Team. The current target environment is the
	    datacenter.</t>
	    <t>This document is not intended to become an RFC.</t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
            <t>This draft is an exploration of the requirements, the
            alternatives, and trade-offs in BGP peer auto-discovery at various
            layers in the stack. It is based on discussions in the IDR WG BGP
            Autoconf Design Team. The current target environment is the
            datacenter.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Design Team Determinations">
            <section title="Problem Scope">
                <t>The current target environment is BGP as used for the underlay
		routing protocol in data center networks. Other scenarios may
		be considered as part of the analysis for this work, but work on
		those environments will be deferred to other efforts.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Simplicity">
		<t>The auto-discovery mechanism is designed to be simple.</t>
		<t>The goal is to select BGP Speakers where a BGP session may be
		successfully negotiated for a particular purpose.  The
		auto-discovery mechanism will not replace or conflict with data
		exchanged by the BGP FSM, including its OPEN message.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="BGP Auto-Discovery Protocol State Requirements">
                <t>
                    <list style="symbols">
			<t>Support for IPv4 and IPv6 address families, but do
			not assume that both are available.</t>
			<t>The ability to use directly attached interface
			addresses, or the device's Loopback address.  When using
			the Loopback address, potentially exchange additional
			information to bootstrap routing to that address.</t>
			<t>Discovery of BGP transport protocol end-points and
			key properties such as IP addresses, authentication
			parameters, layer 3 liveness mechanisms such as
			BFD, and support for GTSM <xref target="RFC5082"/>.</t>
			<!-- XXX JMH What about ports? -->
			<t>Discovery of BGP peer session parameters relevant to
			peer selection such as Autonomous System (AS) Numbers,
			BGP Identifiers, supported address
			families/subsequent-address families (AFI/SAFIs), and
			device roles.</t>
			<t>Device roles are the minimal information available
			for peer selection for a particular application.  While
			some roles may be standardized to provide consistent
			code points, the expectation is that roles will in many
			cases be user-defined. Examples of roles may include things like:
            "I'm at Layer (stage) 3 in the Clos fabric", "I'm a fabric egress
            node", etc.</t>
			<t>Once this information has been learned, a BGP Speaker
			has the necessary information to determine if it wishes to
			open a BGP session with the discovered BGP Speaker.</t>
			<t>The existing BGP finite-state machine (FSM) will then
			be leveraged to do all further work.</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            <section title="BGP Auto-Discovery Protocol Transport Requirements">
	    	<t>BGP Auto-Discovery Protocol State may be carried in multiple
		transport protocols.</t>
		<t>Implementations supporting more than one transport protocol
		for this state must have a mechanism for consistently selecting
		discovered BGP sessions.  The BGP Identifier, which is carried
		by the BGP OPEN message, can help detect sessions to the same
		BGP Speaker carried in multiple transports.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Operator Configuration">
	<!-- XXX JMH - We have configuration requirements for our side, and
	acceptable peer requirements on the other side. -->
            <t>With BGP auto-discovery, some configuration of BGP is still
            needed. Operator configuration should be able to decide at least
            the following:
            <list style="symbols">
                <t>Select or otherwise filter which peers to actually try to
                send BGP OPEN message.</t>
                <t>Decide the parameters to use, for example:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>IP addressing: IPv4 or IPv6</t>
                    <t>Interface for peering: Loopback, or Direct</t>
                    <t>Any special forwarding or routing needed for reaching
                    the prospective peer, for example, loopback.</t>
                    <t>AS numbering.</t>
                    <t>BGP Authentication Options.</t>
                </list></t>
            </list></t>
            <t>In addition to actually forming the BGP sessions, a common
            deplyoment model may also the so called "validation" model. In this
            model, the operator configures the BGP sessions manually, and uses
            the information collected/populated by the BGP Autoconf mechanism
            to validate that the sessions are correct.</t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Considerations on Design Principles">
            <t>This section summarizes the considerations of possible criteria
            for the design of BGP auto-discovery mechanism, which may need
            further discussion in a wider community than the design team (for
	    example, the IDR WG).</t>

	    <section title="Transport Considerations">
		<t>The network layer of the discovery mechanism.  This may
		impact the scoping of the deployment of the auto-discovery
		mechanism.
		    <list style="symbols">
			<t>Layer 2: For example, based on Ethernet.</t>
			<t>Layer 3: Which is generic for any link-layer protocol.</t>
			<!-- XXX JMH - multicast considerations? -->
		    </list>
	    	</t>
	    	<t>Potentially leveraging existing protocols deployed in the data
		center.</t>
	    	<t>The length of message supported by the protocol.</t>
		<t>How extensible the protocol is to carry future state for BGP
		auto-configuration.</t>
	    </section>

            <section title="Relationship with BGP">
	    <t>
            <list style="symbols">
                <t>The auto-discovery mechanism should be independent from BGP
		session establishment of the discovered session.</t>
                <t>Not affect on BGP session establishment and routing
                exchange, other than the interactions for triggering the
                setup/removal of peer session based on discovery mechanism.</t>
		<!-- XXX JMH - Here the example of draft-xu dropping sessions is
		a discussion point -->
                <t>Potentially leveraging existing BGP protocol sessions for
		discovery of new BGP sessions.</t>
            </list></t>
	    </section>

	    <section title="Session Selection Considerations">
		<t>Candidate BGP sessions to a given BGP Speaker may be discovered by one
		or more auto-discovery protocols.  Even for a single protocol, multiple
		transport session endpoints may be discovered for the same BGP Speaker.
		These different sessions may be required for supporting different address
		families such as IPv4/IPv6 depending on the BGP operational practices for
		that device.  Examples include a distinct and matching session for the
		IPv4/IPv6 address family, a unified session carrying IPv4 over IPv6 and
		vice-versa, etc.</t>
		<t>The BGP Identifier (router-id), a required protocol component of BGP,
		can serve to identify the same instance of the BGP Speaker.  This is a
		required element of the information to be carried in the auto-discovery
		protocol.</t>
		<t>When multiple mechanisms exist to discovery the same BGP speaker in an
		implementation, that implementation MUST document the process by which it
		chooses discovered sessions.  Those implementations also MUST describe
		interactions with their protocol state machinery for each mechanism.</t>
	    </section>

        <section title="Operational Trust Considerations">
        <t>Different deployment models will have different trust models and
        requirements. Some of this will be driven by the size, complexity and
        operational practices of the operator. For example, some operators have
        very strict physical protection of the datacenter, and their
        deployment model assumes that anything which plugs into devices in the
        datacenter is, by definition, trusted. Other operators take a very
        different approach, and assume the least amount of trust possible.</t>

        <t>Much of this difference is also reflected in the operator's
        bootstrapping solution. Some operators build individual configurations
        for each device, and manually provision the configuration into the
        non-volatile storage of the device before it is shipped. Other
        operators use solutions similar to PXE Boot to automatically load an
        operating system and configuration onto the device, based on a unique
        device identifier (such as management Ethernet MAC address). Some
        operators pre-configure devices with identical base configurations
        containing some bootstrapping policy logic ("If you are a Model-X
        device, and interface 23 is connected to a device of type Y, then you
        must be at Stage-2 in a Clos fabric") and allow the device to use this
        policy information to infer its role and position. A final set of
        datacenter operators (e.g enterprise) would like to be able to simply
        unpack a new device, plug it in and have the device infer everything
        (it is unclear if this is a deployment model that we want to
        support).</t>

        <t>Many datacenter operators already have a well-developed process for
        installing and bringing up a new datacenter network, complete with
        solutions to bootstrap and configure the network. These operators will
        want to be able to use the BGP Autoconf mechanism to perform validation
        of the datacenter fabric, and ongoing "sanity-checking" to confirm
        that the datacenter is correctly cabled, and that the BGP sessions
        which have been configured from the database match what the
        autodiscovered sessions would have created. Over time, if the
        BGP Autoconf solution proves to be successful, reliable and
        scalabe, operators may begin using it as the primary source of
        record.</t>

        <t>Closely related to these considerations is the "scope" of the
        discovery process. It is expected that many operators will wish to
        only perform discovery on "infrastructure" or "fabric" interfaces, and
        not interfaces which face customers.</t>

        <t>It is not clear that the solution that chosen will be able to
        meet all of the trust and deployment models, and we will need to
        prioritize which set(s) of deployment scenarios are the most important
        for the design team to solve.</t>

        <t>Trust/Operational deployment driven requirements. The solution
        should:
            <list style="symbols">
                <t>Allow operators to determine which classes of interfaces the
                discovery protocol operates on (e.g: "Interfaces numbered 1-17" or
                "Only 100GE interfaces"). This is likely an
                implementation detail.</t>
                <t>Allow operation in a "validation" or "verification" only
                mode, where the Autoconf solution populates a database or model
                showing what sessions it would bring up if allowed.</t>
                <t>Ideally allow for differnt levels of "granularity" in
                pre-configuration. For example, if the protocol is capable of
                autoconfiguring everything, it should also support filtering or
                limiting the session according to configured policy. (Likely an
                implmentation detail)</t>
                <t>Support preconfigured authentication systems. This is an
                area where more discussion is needed! The solution MUST also
                support a "no authentication" mode, and, for extra credit,
                negotiated keying.(?)</t>
                <t>Optionally support non-Ethernet interfaces, such as tunnels.
                (Question - VLANS?!)</t>
            </list></t>
        </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Analysis of Candidate Approaches">
            <section title="BGP Peer Discovery at Layer Two">
                <t>BGP Discovery at Layer-2 would entail finding potential
                peers on a LAN or on Point-to-Point links, discovering their
                Layer-3 attributes such as IP addresses, etc.</t>
                <t>There are two available candidates for peer discovery at
                Layer-2, one is based on Link Layer Discovery Protocol (LLDP),
                the other one is based on Layer 3 Discovery Protocol, L3DL
                <xref target="I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl" />.</t>
                <section title="LLDP based Approach">
                    <t>LLDP is a widely deployed protocol with implementations
                    in most devices in data centers. Currently it only advertises
                    the managment Layer-3 address, but could presumably be
                    extended to include the per-interface addresses.</t>

                    <t>LLDP has a limitation that all information must fit in a
                    single PDU (it does not support fragmentation / a
                    "session"). There is an early LLDPv2 development effort
                    to extend this in the IEEE.</t>
                    <t>
                    <xref target="I-D.acee-idr-lldp-peer-discovery" /> describes
                    how to use the LLDP IETF Organizationally Specific TLV to
                    augment the LLDP TLV set to exchange BGP Config Sub-TLVs
                    signaling:
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>AFI</t>
                        <t>IP address (IPv4 or IPv6)</t>
                        <t>Local AS number</t>
                        <t>Local BGP Identifier (AKA, BGP Router ID)</t>
                        <t>Session Group-ID</t>
                        <t>BGP Session Capabilities</t>
                        <t>Key Chain</t>
                        <t>Local Address (as BGP Next Hop).</t>
                    </list></t>
                </section>
                <section title="L3DL based Approach">
                    <t>L3DL
                    <xref target="I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl" /> is an ongoing
                    development in the IETF LSVR Working Group with the goals
                    of discovering IP Layer-3 attributes of links, such as
                    neighbor IP addressing, logical link IP encapsulation
                    abilities, and link liveness which may then be disseminated
                    for the use of BGP-SPF and similar protocols.</t>
                    <t>L3DL Upper Layer Protocol Configuration,
                    <xref target="I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl-ulpc" />, details
                    signaling the minimal set of parameters needed to start a
                    BGP session with a discovered peer. Details such as
                    loopback peering are handled by attributes in the L3DL
                    protocol itself. The information which can be discovered by
                    L3DL is
                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>AS number</t>
                        <t>Local IP address, IPv4 or IPv6, and</t>
                        <t>BGP Authentication.</t>
                    </list></t>
                    <t>L3DL and L3DL-ULPC have well-specified security
                    mechanisms, see
                    <xref target="I-D.ietf-lsvr-l3dl-signing" />.</t>
                    <t>The functionality of L3DL-ULPC is similar but not quite
                    the same as the needs of IDR Design Team. E.g., L3DL is
                    designed to meet more complex needs. L3DL's predecessor,
                    LSOE
                    <xref target="I-D.ietf-lsvr-lsoe" />, was simpler and might
                    be a better candidate for adaptation. If needed the design
                    of LSOE may be customized for the needs of BGP peer auto-
                    disovery.</t>
                    <t>Unlike LLDP, L3DL has only one implementation, and LSOE
                    has only one open source implementation, and neither is
                    significantly deployed.</t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="BGP peer Discovery at Layer Three">
            <t>Discovery at Layer-3 can assume IP addressability, though the IP
            addresses of potential peers are not known a priori and need to be
            discovered before further negotiation. IP multicast may be a good
            choice to address the above concern.</t>
            <t>The possible problem would appear to discovery at Layer-3 is
            that one may not know whether to use IPv4 or IPv6.  This might be
            exacerbated by the possibility of a potential peer not being on the
            local subnet, and hence broadcast and similar techniques may not be
            applicable. While in data center network or networks in a single
            administrative domain, such issue could be easily solved.</t>
            <t>If one can assume that the BGP session is based on
            point-to-point link, then discovery might try IPv6 link-local or
            even IPv4 link- local. A link broadcast or multicast protocol may
            also be used. For switched or bridged multi-point which is at least
            on the same subnet, VLAN, etc., multicast or broadcasts might be a
            viable approach.</t>
            <t>There are four available candidates for BGP peer discovery at
            Layer-3: One is based on extending BGP with new Hello message for
	    peer auto-discovery. One is based on reusing BGP OPEN message format for peer
	    auto-discovery. One is based on bootstrapping BGP sessions via existing BGP
	    sessions.  One is based upon bootstraping a BGP Route Reflector via the OSPF
	    protocol.
	    </t>
            <section title="New BGP Hello Message based Approach">
                <t>
                <xref target="I-D.xu-idr-neighbor-autodiscovery" /> describes a
                BGP neighbor discovery mechanism which is based on a newly
                defined UDP based BGP Hello message. The BGP Hello message is
                sent in multicast to discover the directly connected BGP peers.
                According to the message header format and the TLVs carried in
                the message, the information which can be signaled is:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>AS number</t>
                    <t>BGP Identifier</t>
                    <t>Accepted ASN list</t>
                    <t>Peering address (IPv4 or IPv6)</t>
                    <t>Local prefix (for loopback)</t>
                    <t>Link attributes</t>
                    <t>Neighbor state</t>
                    <t>BGP Authentication</t>
                </list>
                </t>
		<t>The mechanisms in this draft do not currently handle fragmentation.</t>
		<t>The mechanism in this draft is perhaps unique among the other proposals
		in requiring bi-directional state.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="BGP OPEN Message based Approach">
                <t>
                <xref target="I-D.raszuk-idr-bgp-auto-session-setup" /> describes
                a BGP neighbor discovery mechanism by reusing BGP OPEN message
                format with newly defined UDP port. The message is called BGP
                Session Explorer (BSE) packet and is sent in multicast. Since
                the message format is the same as BGP OPEN, the information
                which can be signaled is:
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>AS number</t>
                    <t>BGP Identifier</t>
                    <t>Peering address</t>
                </list></t>
		<t>The mechanism is currently under-specified with respect to a number of
		similar properties described elsewhere.  A general implication is that
		those properties - and others providing for extensibility of the
		auto-discovery mechanism - would need to be added to the BGP OPEN message
		and deal with the related impacts on the BGP session's finite-state
		machine.</t>
		<t>BGP PDUs, including the OPEN message, may be up to 4k in size.  Since
		this mechanism leverages Layer 3 multicast, a PDU fragmentation mechanism
		may need to be described.</t>
            </section>
	    <section title="Bootstrapping BGP via BGP">
		<t>
		<!-- XXX JMH - draft raszuk auto-discovery covered by patent -->
		<xref target="I-D.raszuk-idr-bgp-auto-discovery"/> describes a
		new BGP address family.  The NLRI carries a Group ID + BGP
		Identifier as the key.  A new BGP Path Attribute carries
		information about the sessions:
		<list style="symbols">
		    <t>AS Number</t>
		    <t>AFI/SAFI</t>
		    <t>BGP Identifier</t>
		    <t>Peer Transport Address</t>
		    <t>Flags to declare a session for information only, to force
		    a reset of a session on parameter changes, etc.</t>
		</list>
		</t>
		<t>Since the BGP auto-discovery state is carried by BGP, it inherits the
		security implications of the underlying BGP session.</t>
		<t>PDU size considerations are identical to those of a BGP UPDATE
		message.</t>
		<t>Similarly, extensibility considerations would rely on either the new
		BGP Path Attribute, or one yet to be defined.</t>
	    </section>
	    <section title="Bootstrapping BGP via OSPF">
	        <t><xref target="I-D.acee-ospf-bgp-rr"/> describes a mechanism to learn BGP
		Route Reflectors via OSPFv2/OSPFv3 LSAs.  Multiple types of scopes are
		defined for these LSAs to help constrain where they are advertised in an
		OSPF domain.</t>
		<t>The BGP Route Reflector TLV contains:
		<list style="symbols">
		    <t>Local AS Number</t>
		    <t>IPv4 or IPv6 Address of the Route Reflector</t>
		    <t>A list of AFI/SAFIs supported by the Route Reflector</t>
		</list>
		</t>
		<t>The BGP Route Reflector TLV may be advertised more than once,
		potentially to describe different IP transport endpoints.</t>
		<t>This mechanism does not provide for security properties of the BGP
		session or transport properties such as BFD or GTSM.</t>
	    </section>
            <section title="Discovery at Layer Seven">
                <t>Peer discovery at Layer-7 requires application layer
                rendezvous mechanisms analogous to those used by LISP,
                <xref target="RFC6830" /> or the Bitcoin Protocol.</t>
                <t>If the infrastructure is at all complex, for example, multi-segment
                or worse, then it will need prior routing/forwarding knowledge
                in order to reach the rendezvous. In a BGP centric deployment
                this could pose a chicken and egg problem.</t>
                <t>Rendezvous approaches may appeal to deployments which favor
                a central control framework.</t>
                <t>On the other hand, those who favor distributed protocols
                will have the classic worries about fragility, redundancy,
                reliability, etc.</t>
            </section>
	    <section title="Link-Local Discovery">
		<t>Some existing BGP auto-configuration mechanisms leverage "point to
		point" addressing schemes to bootstrap BGP sessions.  One example utilizes
		an IP subnet numbered such that it may contain only two hosts - for IPv4,
		a /30 or /31 network; for IPv6 a /127 network.  An additional mechanism
		may leverage <xref target="RFC0826">IPv4 ARP</xref> or
		<xref target="RFC4861">IPv6 Neighbor Discovery</xref> to learn of hosts on
		a subnet.</t>
		<t>Such existing mechanisms do not provide an auto-discovery protocol with
		necessary parameters.  Rather, they simplify configuration by permitting
		BGP session configuration templates to be easily applied to interfaces
		without requiring numbering to be known a priori.</t>
	    </section>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>This document makes no request of IANA.</t>
            <t>Note to RFC Editor: this section may be removed on publication
            as an RFC.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations">
            <t>There are two primary components to be secured in environments
	    utilizing BGP auto-discovery: The BGP transport layer discovered via the
	    protocol, and the auto-discovery protocol itself.
	    </t>

	    <section title="BGP Transport Security Considerations">
		<t>The purpose of the auto-discovery protocol is to ease the setup of BGP
		sessions for various applications, including data-center fabrics.
		However, care must be taken to not permit sessions to be setup outside of
		trusted environments.  It is RECOMMENDED that sessions advertised using
		BGP auto-discovery be protected at the transport layer using mechanisms
		such as TCP-AO <xref target="RFC5925"/>, IPsec <xref target="RFC4301"/>,
		or the deprecated TCP-MD5 <xref target="RFC2385"/>.</t>

		<t>It is thus a requirement that the auto-discovery protocol carry
		sufficient information to determine what transport security is to be used
		when establishing a BGP session.</t>

		<t>All Security Considerations from <xref target="RFC4272"/>, BGP Security
		Vulnerabilities Analysis, continue to apply.</t>
	    </section>

	    <section title="Auto-discovery Protocol Considerations">
		<t>As noted in previous sections, BGP auto-discovery may occur scoped in
		many portions of the network.  The information present in the
		auto-discovery protocol is considered sensitive, since it identifies
		resources running the BGP protocol.  Care should be exercised in avoiding
		inadvertent disclosure of BGP sessions that are configured to permit
		auto-configuration even when BGP session transport security is in use.
		The auto-discovery protocol sets the context for such inadvertent
		disclosure.</t>

		<section title="Potential Scopes of an Auto-discovery Protocol">
		    <t>A Layer 2 unicast protocol targets a known device, potentially
		    discovered through other means.  The targeted device receives the
		    message.  Depending on the Layer 2 environment, other devices on the
		    same link may may be able to observe the protocol messages.  Point to
		    point links may also fall into this category.</t>

		    <t>A Layer 2 multicast protocol targets a group of devices on that
		    Layer 2 multicast domain.  A set of devices in that domain receives
		    the message.  Such messages may cross a number of devices in the
		    domain.  An example of this includes a set of Ethernet switches.</t>

		    <t>A Layer 3 unicast protocol inherits the properties of the Layer 2
		    protocol, and is intended to address a specific address - typically
		    one device. Layer 3 unicast protocols may leverage GTSM for their
		    security.</t>

		    <t>A Layer 3 multicast protocol addresses a group of devices in a
		    given multicast domain.  Such domains may be scoped, such as a single
		    link's "All-Routers" group or perhaps all devices subscribed to a
		    specific multicast group in a network.  In many cases, a Layer 3
		    multicast protocol inherits the properties of the Layer 2 multicast
		    protocol.  Link-local scoped multicast protocols may be able to
		    leverage GTSM.</t>

		    <t>A Layer 7 protocol is scoped per the mechanism in the underlying
		    protocol.  IGPs such as OSPF and IS-IS provide an "internal" scoping.
		    BGP, depending on the deployment of the underlying address family, may
		    vary from a targeted advertisement, to Internet-wide.</t>

		    <t>Each of these scopes provide different opportunities for
		    inadvertent disclosure.  The auto-discovery protocol will need to
		    address how the desired security properties interact with the protocol
		    scope.</t>
		</section>

		<section title="Desired Security Properties of the Auto-discovery Protocols">
		    <t>Data Integrity is a required property.  The data that is
		    transmitted by a speaker fo the auto-configuration protocol should be
		    able to pass among its speakers properly.</t>

		    <t>Peer Entity authentication is a required property for Layer 2 and
		    Layer 3 implementations.  In a Layer 7 protocol, that protocol may
		    provide the necessary authentication.</t>

		    <t>Confidentiality is an optional property.  There is a tension
		    between the desire to provide for a simple auto-configuration protocol
		    that is easy to diagnose and debug with inadvertent disclosure.</t>

		    <t>The auto-configuration protocol must be resistant to Denial of
		    Service, and to causing Denial of Service to discovered BGP session
		    end-points.</t>
		</section>
	    </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Acknowledgments">
            <t>The IDR BGP Auto-Conf Design Team.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
	    &RFC2119;
	</references>
        <references title="Informative References">
	    &LLDP;
	    &L3DL;
	    &AUTO-SESSION;
	    &RASZUK-AUTODISCOVERY;
	    &XU-AUTODISCOVERY;
	    &L3DL-SIGNING;
	    &L3DL-ULPC;
	    &LSOE;
	    &BGP-OSPF;
	    &RFC0826;
	    &RFC2385;
	    &RFC3352;
	    &RFC4272;
	    &RFC4301;
	    &RFC4861;
	    &RFC5082;
	    &RFC5925;
	    &RFC6830;
	</references>
    </back>
</rfc>
